<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	
	>
<channel>
	<title>Comments on: Promising difficulties</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/</link>
	<description>Just another WordPress site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 21:49:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.10</generator>
	<item>
		<title>By: Ben</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-227</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 03:24:33 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-227</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Nice article Jerome. One of the messages or examples we have been using for the last year when talking about various styles of visualisation and when focused on story telling or exploratory visualisations is that of Angry Birds. Angry Birds is not a straight forward game in the later levels, with multiple bird types, different actions, the need to get angles right etc. But the first levels are...the game achieves something very few data visualisations do which is immediate engagement ultimately leading to education of the user/player/viewer ultimately giving the viewer the skills and knowledge necessary to handle more complex levels. This is common in many good games and increasingly so in casual games but is at its peak in Angry Birds. 

While I won&#039;t dismiss the need for &quot;academic papers&quot; on this topic, I think that if we looked a little outside the realm many visualisation academics focus on and sought to learn from what the arena of Game Design we would potentially jump start a lot of this understanding and ultimately create visualisations which are at the same time immediately engaging with a rich narrative for exploration underpinning it.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Nice article Jerome. One of the messages or examples we have been using for the last year when talking about various styles of visualisation and when focused on story telling or exploratory visualisations is that of Angry Birds. Angry Birds is not a straight forward game in the later levels, with multiple bird types, different actions, the need to get angles right etc. But the first levels are&#8230;the game achieves something very few data visualisations do which is immediate engagement ultimately leading to education of the user/player/viewer ultimately giving the viewer the skills and knowledge necessary to handle more complex levels. This is common in many good games and increasingly so in casual games but is at its peak in Angry Birds. </p>
<p>While I won&#8217;t dismiss the need for &#8220;academic papers&#8221; on this topic, I think that if we looked a little outside the realm many visualisation academics focus on and sought to learn from what the arena of Game Design we would potentially jump start a lot of this understanding and ultimately create visualisations which are at the same time immediately engaging with a rich narrative for exploration underpinning it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Dino Citraro</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-226</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dino Citraro]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 18:26:41 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-226</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Excellent piece, Jerome.  Thank you for writing it, and thanks for your careful scrutiny of the subject.

Do you think a part of this discussion relates to the expectations of the nomenclature? It seems that the phrases &quot;information visualization&quot; and &quot;data visualization&quot; are getting used interchangeably, when they probably shouldn&#039;t.  When Stephen Few says &quot;Long-term recall is rarely the purpose of information visualization&quot;, do you think he really means &quot;Long-term recall is rarely the purpose of data visualization&quot; ?

Data seems to lend itself (in general) to short-term recall (dashboards, instrument readings, etc) while information is something that might take longer to process, and be a benefit a person more in the long-term.

Things get complicated when visualizations provide both data and information, which many do these days, and still more complicated when people try to discuss them as a single thing, with a single purpose.

The work we do at Periscopic never really starts with a discussion about which type of visualization we will make, but rather what kind of data and information will best inform the subject. Not sure if that is a good or a bad thing...  must think more about it.

It&#039;s exciting to see these concepts evolve and be refined publicly like this.  Thanks again for the post.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Excellent piece, Jerome.  Thank you for writing it, and thanks for your careful scrutiny of the subject.</p>
<p>Do you think a part of this discussion relates to the expectations of the nomenclature? It seems that the phrases &#8220;information visualization&#8221; and &#8220;data visualization&#8221; are getting used interchangeably, when they probably shouldn&#8217;t.  When Stephen Few says &#8220;Long-term recall is rarely the purpose of information visualization&#8221;, do you think he really means &#8220;Long-term recall is rarely the purpose of data visualization&#8221; ?</p>
<p>Data seems to lend itself (in general) to short-term recall (dashboards, instrument readings, etc) while information is something that might take longer to process, and be a benefit a person more in the long-term.</p>
<p>Things get complicated when visualizations provide both data and information, which many do these days, and still more complicated when people try to discuss them as a single thing, with a single purpose.</p>
<p>The work we do at Periscopic never really starts with a discussion about which type of visualization we will make, but rather what kind of data and information will best inform the subject. Not sure if that is a good or a bad thing&#8230;  must think more about it.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s exciting to see these concepts evolve and be refined publicly like this.  Thanks again for the post.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Jakob</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-225</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jakob]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 16:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-225</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Great post! Excuse me, if the following stream of thoughts lacks context...

Having to reconcile conflicting forces is actually one of the key aspects of cognitive science. Heck, a whole theory to explain language acquisition and communication that is based on a conflict resolution heuristic has become the mainstream theory of almost all linguistic disciplines. It would be really surprising if visualization were exempt from this phenomenon.

Much like OT poses for utterances I would assume that in visualizations there&#039;s a sweet spot, a goldilocks position of difficulty, that works best for the specific constraints of a given task. Since a visualization is but a very elaborate signifier for a complex proposition the cognitive mechanisms for communication apply which means, that the degree of difficulty to parse the signifier will be interpreted by the recipient to be indicative of something.

When we look beyond what is overtly stated by the semiotic entities of a visualization we are entering a meta level of communication. We enrich the meaning of signifiers beyond their truth values by contextualizing world knowledge and our expectations of the communication game - the assumption that the sender of a message actually wants to engage in meaningful conversation being just one of them.

So without having a clear idea of how to apply the cross-disciplinary theorems to visualization I&#039;d like to just throw one more thing out there, regarding the paper in question. If we look at the concept of cognitive dissonance, we know that it has been utilized to make messages captivating and memorable. Perhaps creating this feeling of discomfort in the mind, nudging it to reiterate its assessment of the signifiers put in front of it, is what the right degree of &quot;difficulty&quot; accomplishes.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Great post! Excuse me, if the following stream of thoughts lacks context&#8230;</p>
<p>Having to reconcile conflicting forces is actually one of the key aspects of cognitive science. Heck, a whole theory to explain language acquisition and communication that is based on a conflict resolution heuristic has become the mainstream theory of almost all linguistic disciplines. It would be really surprising if visualization were exempt from this phenomenon.</p>
<p>Much like OT poses for utterances I would assume that in visualizations there&#8217;s a sweet spot, a goldilocks position of difficulty, that works best for the specific constraints of a given task. Since a visualization is but a very elaborate signifier for a complex proposition the cognitive mechanisms for communication apply which means, that the degree of difficulty to parse the signifier will be interpreted by the recipient to be indicative of something.</p>
<p>When we look beyond what is overtly stated by the semiotic entities of a visualization we are entering a meta level of communication. We enrich the meaning of signifiers beyond their truth values by contextualizing world knowledge and our expectations of the communication game &#8211; the assumption that the sender of a message actually wants to engage in meaningful conversation being just one of them.</p>
<p>So without having a clear idea of how to apply the cross-disciplinary theorems to visualization I&#8217;d like to just throw one more thing out there, regarding the paper in question. If we look at the concept of cognitive dissonance, we know that it has been utilized to make messages captivating and memorable. Perhaps creating this feeling of discomfort in the mind, nudging it to reiterate its assessment of the signifiers put in front of it, is what the right degree of &#8220;difficulty&#8221; accomplishes.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: jerome</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-224</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 14:25:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-224</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Hi Thorri, well the idea is that it makes you slow down but after you accelerate. maybe a dog crossing the road? hopefully those are not associated with bah-bumps in the collective mind :)]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi Thorri, well the idea is that it makes you slow down but after you accelerate. maybe a dog crossing the road? hopefully those are not associated with bah-bumps in the collective mind 🙂</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Thorlakur Ludviksson</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-223</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Thorlakur Ludviksson]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 14:15:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-223</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Hi Jerome, good article. I think you&#039;re spot on with the distinction of visualizations.

But I propose new metaphors: 
- Instead of &quot;speedbumps&quot;. Desirable difficulties are &quot;Narrow roads&quot;. (Speedbumps remind us of the uncomfortable feeling of bah-bump as the car stumbles over a that lump in the road.)
- Cognitive efficiency will then be a &quot;highway&quot;.

Cheers!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi Jerome, good article. I think you&#8217;re spot on with the distinction of visualizations.</p>
<p>But I propose new metaphors:<br />
&#8211; Instead of &#8220;speedbumps&#8221;. Desirable difficulties are &#8220;Narrow roads&#8221;. (Speedbumps remind us of the uncomfortable feeling of bah-bump as the car stumbles over a that lump in the road.)<br />
&#8211; Cognitive efficiency will then be a &#8220;highway&#8221;.</p>
<p>Cheers!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: Jorge Camoes</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-222</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jorge Camoes]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 00:25:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-222</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Jerome, a few years ago I wrote a post in my Portuguese blog titled &quot;Can a good chart be dangerous?&quot; (&quot;good&quot; in the sense of &quot;effective&quot;). To tell you the truth, actively adding a speed bump to reduce a chart effectiveness never crossed my mind, but I wrote that an overly optimized chart could trigger some adverse side effects (passive acceptance).

As you know, from the &quot;effectiveness&quot; point of view adding desirable difficulties amounts to heresy. Solving the problem with data (adding more detail) is a more palatable option, but it&#039;s the end result that matters, and we shouldn&#039;t close the door to lateral thinking. We really need it.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jerome, a few years ago I wrote a post in my Portuguese blog titled &#8220;Can a good chart be dangerous?&#8221; (&#8220;good&#8221; in the sense of &#8220;effective&#8221;). To tell you the truth, actively adding a speed bump to reduce a chart effectiveness never crossed my mind, but I wrote that an overly optimized chart could trigger some adverse side effects (passive acceptance).</p>
<p>As you know, from the &#8220;effectiveness&#8221; point of view adding desirable difficulties amounts to heresy. Solving the problem with data (adding more detail) is a more palatable option, but it&#8217;s the end result that matters, and we shouldn&#8217;t close the door to lateral thinking. We really need it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: jerome</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-221</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 00:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-221</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Hi Jan Willem, this reminds me that I should post something on my own intervention at visweek which was precisely on what you say, hopefully sometimes before visweek 2012
cheers!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi Jan Willem, this reminds me that I should post something on my own intervention at visweek which was precisely on what you say, hopefully sometimes before visweek 2012<br />
cheers!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: jerome</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-220</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 00:16:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-220</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Absolutely - excessive cognitive load is a game-stopper. those &quot;desirable difficulties&quot; have to be moderate. If the slope is too steep, even if I accelerate I can&#039;t get past (or so I&#039;ve heard, I don&#039;t drive. Is that how cars work?). and just because this effect has worked in some settings it is definitely not a license to try anything. 
I&#039;ve used the mortgage fraud thing as an example where there is little cognitive load and where preattentive attributes work. Even if you don&#039;t know what this is about you see instantly the 2 crossed squares and you get the intuition that they are points of interest. It would be a pity if the system somehow got in the way of that and added chartjunk or whatever so you could interpret this better. A Palantir analyst who is able to create this view is not likely to appreciate the attention.
for the flower things, you&#039;re right - the main point is not really to convey information, or at least not in the petals. But the goal of this specific visualization is the means in desirable difficulties, that is to create  5 minutes on that page on average, versus a handful of seconds elsewhere on pretty much any page of the OECD site. Through this visualization I was comforted in the idea that different representations can engagement. It would not have been too difficult to represent every data point used to create the flowers in a very neat dashboard. Would we have had the same level of user commitment? People stay aroundreally enhance engagement which can in turn have benefits, although, yes, it is to the expense of the transparency of the information.]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Absolutely &#8211; excessive cognitive load is a game-stopper. those &#8220;desirable difficulties&#8221; have to be moderate. If the slope is too steep, even if I accelerate I can&#8217;t get past (or so I&#8217;ve heard, I don&#8217;t drive. Is that how cars work?). and just because this effect has worked in some settings it is definitely not a license to try anything.<br />
I&#8217;ve used the mortgage fraud thing as an example where there is little cognitive load and where preattentive attributes work. Even if you don&#8217;t know what this is about you see instantly the 2 crossed squares and you get the intuition that they are points of interest. It would be a pity if the system somehow got in the way of that and added chartjunk or whatever so you could interpret this better. A Palantir analyst who is able to create this view is not likely to appreciate the attention.<br />
for the flower things, you&#8217;re right &#8211; the main point is not really to convey information, or at least not in the petals. But the goal of this specific visualization is the means in desirable difficulties, that is to create  5 minutes on that page on average, versus a handful of seconds elsewhere on pretty much any page of the OECD site. Through this visualization I was comforted in the idea that different representations can engagement. It would not have been too difficult to represent every data point used to create the flowers in a very neat dashboard. Would we have had the same level of user commitment? People stay aroundreally enhance engagement which can in turn have benefits, although, yes, it is to the expense of the transparency of the information.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: jerome</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-219</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 00:01:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-219</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[well, this subject has been on our common agenda under different guises. so I suppose we will discuss it live next time we meet!

you are raising good questions and I struggle to give a concise answer. I agree that the notion of difficulty is counter-intuitive, yet I&#039;ve seen this pattern outside of visualization so I can accept it in theory, with the caveat that not just any difficulty can work. I note however that not everyone agrees on what constitues cognitive cost. For instance, Few and Hullman disagree about small multiples vs animation. Hullman says that small multiples have a higher cost because passively viewing a flow of images requires less effort than acquiring information piece by piece by looking at each small multiple in turn, in other words receiving information is easier with animation. But Few says that small multiple have a lower cost because comparing across several multiples - which are there to see - is much easier than across several frames of animation, so manipulating the information is easier with small multiples. 
My intuition is that visual difficulties may work very early in the process (ie a non-orthodox, yet grammar-of-graphics complient representation) rather than later (no need to annoy the user once they are sold in the concept). Yet again I see NYT graphics holding the hand of the viewer and effectively controlling the pace throughout the whole time. 
the great thing is, no matter what, in the next year we&#039;ll see thought-provoking visualizations or apps that will try to implement that. Some will work, some will fail, but certainly there will be someone to comment!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>well, this subject has been on our common agenda under different guises. so I suppose we will discuss it live next time we meet!</p>
<p>you are raising good questions and I struggle to give a concise answer. I agree that the notion of difficulty is counter-intuitive, yet I&#8217;ve seen this pattern outside of visualization so I can accept it in theory, with the caveat that not just any difficulty can work. I note however that not everyone agrees on what constitues cognitive cost. For instance, Few and Hullman disagree about small multiples vs animation. Hullman says that small multiples have a higher cost because passively viewing a flow of images requires less effort than acquiring information piece by piece by looking at each small multiple in turn, in other words receiving information is easier with animation. But Few says that small multiple have a lower cost because comparing across several multiples &#8211; which are there to see &#8211; is much easier than across several frames of animation, so manipulating the information is easier with small multiples.<br />
My intuition is that visual difficulties may work very early in the process (ie a non-orthodox, yet grammar-of-graphics complient representation) rather than later (no need to annoy the user once they are sold in the concept). Yet again I see NYT graphics holding the hand of the viewer and effectively controlling the pace throughout the whole time.<br />
the great thing is, no matter what, in the next year we&#8217;ll see thought-provoking visualizations or apps that will try to implement that. Some will work, some will fail, but certainly there will be someone to comment!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>By: jerome</title>
		<link>/2011/11/13/promising-difficulties/#comment-218</link>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2011 23:35:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1111#comment-218</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Hi Jorge, I think we can all agree on &quot;undesirable difficulties&quot;. Social networks make these charts more visible now and I sometimes feel like Pandora&#039;s box has been opened. There is a form of unhealthy emulation and escalation in outrage to common sense. 

The reason why I wrote this is not to defend such practices, although to be honest I&#039;m quite grateful that designers out there try such extreme forms because&lt;a href=&quot;http://fellinlovewithdata.com/reflections/demystifying-cargo-cult-visualization-you-cannot-visualize-3-variables-by-mixing-3-colors&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt; they can be studied&lt;/a&gt;. But rather, to say that desirable difficulties is something entirely different. They are speed bumps, rather than roadblocks. It&#039;s not about trying to deviate from commonly accepted representations as much as possible. And in fact, we don&#039;t quite know what&#039;s the best way to set them up. that&#039;s why I am looking forward to more papers on this!]]></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi Jorge, I think we can all agree on &#8220;undesirable difficulties&#8221;. Social networks make these charts more visible now and I sometimes feel like Pandora&#8217;s box has been opened. There is a form of unhealthy emulation and escalation in outrage to common sense. </p>
<p>The reason why I wrote this is not to defend such practices, although to be honest I&#8217;m quite grateful that designers out there try such extreme forms because<a href="http://fellinlovewithdata.com/reflections/demystifying-cargo-cult-visualization-you-cannot-visualize-3-variables-by-mixing-3-colors" rel="nofollow"> they can be studied</a>. But rather, to say that desirable difficulties is something entirely different. They are speed bumps, rather than roadblocks. It&#8217;s not about trying to deviate from commonly accepted representations as much as possible. And in fact, we don&#8217;t quite know what&#8217;s the best way to set them up. that&#8217;s why I am looking forward to more papers on this!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
