<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>presentation &#8211; jeromecukier.net</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/tag/presentation/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Just another WordPress site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 05:36:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.10</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Don&#8217;t take my word for it</title>
		<link>/2011/11/24/dont-take-my-word-for-it/</link>
		<comments>/2011/11/24/dont-take-my-word-for-it/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2011 01:18:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[presentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interaction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[model]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[persuasion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[politics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rhetorics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[visweek]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1126</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Inspiration In June 2010, I attended a Wolfram&#124;Alpha event called the London Computational Knowledge Summit where speakers mostly focused on how computers can transform the way we teach and transmit knowledge. Several of the presentations made a lasting impression, and mostly the talk by Jon McLoone: Jon&#8217;s point was that academic papers today look an <a class="read-more" href="/2011/11/24/dont-take-my-word-for-it/">&#8230;&#160;<span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Inspiration</h2>
<p>In June 2010, I attended a Wolfram|Alpha event called the London Computational Knowledge Summit where speakers mostly focused on how computers can transform the way we teach and transmit knowledge. Several of the presentations made a lasting impression, and mostly the talk by Jon McLoone:</p>
<pre><code><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/tizMNn6xKFw?version=3&amp;start=380&amp;wmode=transparent" width="600" height="362" style="background-color:#000;display:block;margin-bottom:0;max-width:100%;" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe><p style="font-size:11px;margin-top:0;"><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tizMNn6xKFw" target="_blank" title="Watch on YouTube">Watch this video on YouTube</a>.</p></code></pre>
<p>Jon&#8217;s point was that academic papers today look an awful lot like those in the 17th century. Granted, they&#8217;re not in latin, they can be displayed online and there is color, but as far as maths are concerned it&#8217;s still long pages of difficult language and long formulas. The computer, however, can do so much more than transmit information. In the clip above (around 6&#8217;20&#8221;) Jon shows how a paper on edge detection can be much more effective if instead of using a static example to demonstrate the technique, the paper were able to use a live example, such as input from the camera. In that talk and throughout the day, there were more examples on how interactive displays could be useful for teaching.</p>
<p>Teaching, telling stories and getting a message across use similar functions. Fast forward to VisWeek 2010 and the first &#8220;<a href="http://thevcl.com/storytelling/">Telling Stories with Data</a>&#8221; workshop. Some of the presentations there (I&#8217;m thinking of <a href="http://thevcl.com/storytelling/speakers.html#nicholas_diakopoulos">Nick Diakopoulos</a> and <a href="http://thevcl.com/storytelling/speakers.html#matthias_shapiro">Matthias Shapiro</a> mostly) hinted that <strong>there could be a process</strong> through which readers/users/audience could be taken through so <strong>they can make the most of an intended message</strong>. Interestingly, this process is not about transmitting as much data as effortlessly as possible but rather to engage the audience, to get them to challenge their assumptions.</p>
<p>Those two events really made me pause and think. Ever since I had started working in visualization, all my efforts had been focused on being as clear as possible, and my focus, on efficient visuals. However, for some tasks, <strong>clarity just isn&#8217;t optimal</strong>. That wasn&#8217;t much of an issue in most of my OECD work where such an approach makes a lot of sense but I started seeing that there was a world of possibility when it comes to changing people&#8217;s perception on a subject or even persuading them.</p>
<h2>Application</h2>
<h3>French pension reform</h3>
<p>Right at the moment of visWeek 2010, France was plagued by strikes against the proposed pension reform. At the peak of contestation up to 3m people demonstrated (that&#8217;s as much as one adult out of 14). I was quite irritated by the protests. In theory, left and right had very comparable views on this problem and only disagreed on unsignificant details. They both knew reform was unavoidable, and, again, had similar plans. But when those of the current government were implemented, the opposition capitalized on the discontent and attacked the plan vigorously. <strong>Their rethoric were entirely verbal</strong> &#8211; no numbers were harmed in the making of their discourse! Consequently, protesters and a large part of the population started to develop notions about the state of pensions which were completely disconnected from reality.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://jeromecukier.net/stuff/visweek/datastories/index.html"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1143" title="retraites" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/retraites.png" alt="" width="721" height="540" /></a></p>
<p>I believe that if numbers had been used early enough, it would have been enough to provide a counterpoint to such fallacies and while it may not have prevented demonstrations, it would have greatly helped to dampen their effect. With that in mind and with official data I tried to build a model to show what would happen if one changed this or that parameter of pension policy. Pension mechanics are quite simple: what you give on one side, you take on another; the evolution of population is quite well known, so making such a model is pretty straight forward. But putting that in a visual application really showed how the current situation was unsustainable. In this application I challenge the user to find a solution &#8211; any solution &#8211; to the pension problem, by using the same levers as the policy makers. It turns out that there is just one viable possibility. Yet, letting people find that by themselves and challenge that idea as hard as they could was very different from paternalizing and telling people that this was just the way it is.</p>
<p>On the course of the year I got involved in several occasions in situations like this where data visualization could be used to influence people&#8217;s opinion, and likewise I tried to use that approach. Instead of sending a top-down message (with or without data), instead confront the assumptions of the audience and get them to interact with a model. After this experience, their perception will have changed. This technique doesn&#8217;t try to bypass the viewers critical thinking, but instead to leverage their intelligence.</p>
<h3>In politics</h3>
<p>I am very concerned with the use of data visualization in politics for many reasons. One of them is because I&#8217;m a public servant. In my experience, most decisions are not taken by politicians, but by experts or technicians who are commited to the public good. Yet, when poorly  explained, these decisions can be misunderstood and attacked. Visualization, I believe, can help defend such decisions (those who are justifiable at least) and explain them better to a greater number.</p>
<p>Although a lot of data is available out there (or perhaps for that very reason) only few people have a good grasp of the economic situation of their country. This just can&#8217;t be helped. It&#8217;s not possible to increase the percentage of people who can guestimate the unemployment rate and it&#8217;s not really important. Very few people need to know such a number, now what is important is to be able to use that information in context when it is useful. For instance, at election time, a voter should be able to know if the incumbent has created or destroyed jobs. This is something that data visualization can handle brilliantly.</p>
<p>Finally, my issue with political communication is that it is written by activists, for activists. It works well to motivate people with a certain sensitivity but it is not very effective at getting others to change side. This is a bias which is difficult to detect by those in charge of political communications because, well, they&#8217;re activits too&#8230; and here this flavor of model-based data visualization, with its appearance of objectivity and neutrality, can complement the more verbal aspect of rhetoric quite well.</p>
<p>In the talk I used Al Gore&#8217;s <em>An Inconvenient Truth </em>as a counter example. This movie is a fine example of story-telling, and operating at an emotional rather that at a rational novel. I trust that people who feel concerned about climate change will be reinforced in their beliefs after seeing the movie. However, those who do not were unconvinced. In fact, the movie also gave a strong boost to climate skeptics. There was a real barrage of blog posts and websites attempting to debunk the assertions of that &#8220;truth&#8221;, most often with data. There is a missed opportunity: if the really well-made stories of the movie had been complemented with a climate model that people could experiment with, it would have been perceived as less monolithic, less manichean, less dogmatic.</p>
<h2>The conclusions</h2>
<p>In my practice using an interactive model can help <strong>a lot</strong> to get a message across (and no, I don&#8217;t have a rigorous evaluation for &#8220;a lot&#8221;, that&#8217;s the advantage of not being an academic).</p>
<p>Such models <strong>engage the users</strong>, they come out as <strong>more objective and truthful</strong> as static representations, and they can be very useful to <strong>address preconceptions</strong>. Chances are they&#8217;re more fun, too.</p>
<p>Then again, just because a model is interactive and built on transparent data and equations doesn&#8217;t mean it&#8217;s objective. It is usually possible to <strong>control the model</strong> or the interface so that one interpretation is more likely than the other, and that&#8217;s precisely the point if you are using data visualization to influence.</p>
<p>It can be very cheap and easy to turn a static representation into an interactive display. Every chart with more than 2 dimensions can be turned in a visualization where the user controls one dimension and sees data for the others evolve.</p>
<p>And if you build a model like this, you must be very open and transparent about the data and the equations and sometimes find ways to get people to overcome their doubts.</p>
<p>Besides, having a working interactive model is no guarantee of success. You really have to be careful that your users are not likely to interpret your visualization in ways you never intended.</p>
<h2>The presentation</h2>
<p><iframe src="https://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/10279298" width="400" height="337" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe><br/><br />
All examples I used in the presentation both good and bad, both mine and others can be found at <a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/data-stories/">http://www.jeromecukier.net/data-stories/</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/11/24/dont-take-my-word-for-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Experiencing the sexperience 1000</title>
		<link>/2011/09/05/experiencing-the-sexperience-1000/</link>
		<comments>/2011/09/05/experiencing-the-sexperience-1000/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2011 11:25:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[data visualization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web sites]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sexperience]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[survey]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tabulated]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=1044</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[If you think of data visualization as a great way to bring together heaps of interesting data and, well, a visual language, one of the most exciting areas in terms of room for improvement has to be how surveys are visualized. In conversations with my pollster friend @laguirlande, I often find myself regretting that when <a class="read-more" href="/2011/09/05/experiencing-the-sexperience-1000/">&#8230;&#160;<span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you think of data visualization as a great way to bring together heaps of interesting data and, well, a visual language, one of the most exciting areas in terms of room for improvement has to be how surveys are visualized.<br />
In conversations with my pollster friend <a href="http://www.twitter.com/#!/laguirlande">@laguirlande</a>, I often find myself regretting that when reading an opinion survey, we see answer tallies in isolation. That is: we can see what proportion of people gave the first answer to question A, and what proportion of people gave the second answer to question B. But what we we <em>don&#8217;t</em> know is, out of the first group, how many find themselves in the second?<br />
Another frustration: survey data is very tabulated. Pollsters know respondents age, gender, and all kind of categories they can fit their respondents in. But again when reading the results, more often than not it is not possible to utilize this structure to filter answers by category &#8211; do men react like women to the issue?<br />
Yet opinion surveys are always interesting and topical, else they wouldn&#8217;t be paid for. And the interestingness may lie there: little nuggets of data that could have escaped analysts could be found by readers as they try various manipulations.</p>
<p>And then last week, Chanel 4 released the <a href="http://sexperienceuk.channel4.com/the-sexperience-1000">sexperience 1000</a>, a project around the &#8220;Great British Sex Survey&#8221; by Ipsos MORI, which as its name implies is a large-scale survey on sexual practices of UK citizens.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">The project walks us through around 20 questions where little icons represent individual respondents. When the reader changes questions, the icons arrange themselves in bars or circles to form a chart.<br />
<a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience1.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1046" title="sexperience1" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience1.png" alt="" width="720" height="454" /></a></p>
<h3>Yes, filtering! Yes, cross-tabulating!</h3>
<p style="text-align: left;">It is then possible to click on a column label to &#8220;track&#8221; that group and find out what they&#8217;ve been up to.<br />
Here, for instance, we can select the group of people who had over 101 partners and follow them through another question: the longest period without intercourse, for instance.<br />
<a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience2.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1046" title="sexperience2" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience2.png" alt="" width="720" height="454" /></a><br />
The selected individuals will show in green, so we can see that some of them went through long periods of abstinence.<br />
<a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience3.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1046" title="sexperience2" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience3.png" alt="" width="720" height="454" /></a></p>
<p>It is also possible to select one interesting individual and see all of their answers.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">It is also possible to filter the individuals according to many categories. Here, for instance, we can see that a majority of respondents had intercourse in a car. Including quite a few who don&#8217;t drive or don&#8217;t have a car!<br />
<a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience4.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1046" title="sexperience2" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience4.png" alt="" width="720" height="454" /></a><br />
<a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience5.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1046" title="sexperience2" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience5.png" alt="" width="720" height="454" /></a></p>
<h3>Great interactivity, yet legibility could be improved</h3>
<p>Those functions are truly great and encourage the reader to explore. Yet the choice of representation makes it a bit difficult to understand the answers.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience1.png"><img title="sexperience1" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience1.png" alt="" width="720" height="454" /></a><br />
Going back to the first chart I showed about the number of partners for instance, this representation highlights the <em>mode</em>, the most frequent answer to the question. In this case, this is the 11-20 bracket with 121 answers. A close second is just 1 partner (120 answers). The composition of the answer brackets has a lot of influence on that, because if we had made a 5-9 bracket for instance it would have outweighed both (217). Also, they chose not to directly represent the people who had 0 partners, which are over 7% of the respondents.<br />
More fundamentally, I suppose that people want to know where do they fit in the distribution. Are they normal? Less then the norm? Or better? From that chart it&#8217;s very difficult.<br />
With that in mind, it&#8217;s more relevant to show a cumulative chart.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexsurvey1.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1053" title="sexsurvey" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexsurvey1.png" alt="" /></a><br />
Less than 5! who would have known?</p>
<p>The site choose to display bar charts when the answer is quantitative, but to present circles for qualitative questions. This is fine when several circles are displayed: it&#8217;s ok to figure out if one is bigger than the other.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience71.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1052" title="sexperience7" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience71.png" alt="" width="720" height="454" /></a></p>
<p>But it&#8217;s much harder when only one is shown, like for the question on places I&#8217;ve shown above. It&#8217;s difficult to know whether this is a &#8220;big circle&#8221; or &#8220;small circle&#8221; without any indication of the total size of the sample. I only know that the majority of respondents had intercourse in a car because of the small number 550 next to the circle, but there is no graphical way to show that.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">It&#8217;s even harder to compare proportions across groups which have different sizes.<br />
<a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience6.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1046" title="sexperience2" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/09/sexperience6.png" alt="" width="720" height="454" /></a></p>
<p>Here, for instance, I&#8217;m trying to see whether people with an iPhone are more likely to cheat on their partners. What I see is two grey bubbles &#8211; it&#8217;s relatively easy to say that one is bigger than the other &#8211; then two smaller blue and pink ones, which are harder to compare one to another because they are smaller. What&#8217;s even harder is to assess whether the ratio between the larger balls is greater or smaller than the one between the smaller balls. However, the proportion between both balls (that is the share of the respondents who have an iPhone) is relatively easy to figure out, too bad it doesn&#8217;t answer the question at all.<br />
To compare across groups of different size, you just can&#8217;t escape switching to proportions. I understand the design choice and enjoy its consistency but in this case it goes against the function of the site. I feel that in this case, the designers chose playability and aesthetic appeal over ease of getting questions answered, which is not a bad choice per se condidering the subject and audience, even if there are more academic possibilities. At any rate, the Sexperience 1000 shows the way survey results could be displayed and is a great improvement over the current situation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2011/09/05/experiencing-the-sexperience-1000/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Slideshare.net 2009 contest: I&#8217;m endorsing Dan Roam</title>
		<link>/2009/09/02/slidesharenet-2009-contest-im-endorsing-dan-roam/</link>
		<comments>/2009/09/02/slidesharenet-2009-contest-im-endorsing-dan-roam/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2009 15:23:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[book review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[contest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dan roam]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[slideshare]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=212</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Healthcare Napkins All View more documents from Dan Roam. Slideshare 2009 contest is up again, and there&#8217;s about 1 week to vote. For the contest, I&#8217;m endorsing Dan Roam and counting on everyone to vote for him and support his presentation. Previous winners of the contest include Shift happens or Thirst who got a lot <a class="read-more" href="/2009/09/02/slidesharenet-2009-contest-im-endorsing-dan-roam/">&#8230;&#160;<span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="__ss_1867808" style="width: 425px; text-align: left;"><a style="font:14px Helvetica,Arial,Sans-serif;display:block;margin:12px 0 3px 0;text-decoration:underline;" title="Healthcare Napkins All" href="http://www.slideshare.net/danroam/healthcare-napkins-all">Healthcare Napkins All</a><object classid="clsid:d27cdb6e-ae6d-11cf-96b8-444553540000" width="425" height="355" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=6,0,40,0"><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always" /><param name="src" value="http://static.slidesharecdn.com/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=healthcarenapkinall-090816001957-phpapp01&amp;rel=0&amp;stripped_title=healthcare-napkins-all" /><param name="allowfullscreen" value="true" /><embed type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="425" height="355" src="http://static.slidesharecdn.com/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=healthcarenapkinall-090816001957-phpapp01&amp;rel=0&amp;stripped_title=healthcare-napkins-all" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true"></embed></object></p>
<div style="font-size: 11px; font-family: tahoma,arial; height: 26px; padding-top: 2px;">View more <a style="text-decoration:underline;" href="http://www.slideshare.net/">documents</a> from <a style="text-decoration:underline;" href="http://www.slideshare.net/danroam">Dan Roam</a>.</div>
</div>
<p><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/contest/worlds-best-presentation-contest-2009/entries?order=popularity">Slideshare 2009 contest</a> is up again, and there&#8217;s about 1 week to vote. For the contest, I&#8217;m endorsing Dan Roam and counting on everyone to <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/contest/worlds-best-presentation-contest-2009/entries?order=popularity">vote </a>for him and support his <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/danroam/healthcare-napkins-all">presentation</a>. Previous winners of the contest include <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jbrenman/shift-happens-33834">Shift happens</a> or <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jbrenman/thirst">Thirst</a> who got a lot of coverage and views. I think that Dan&#8217;s unique presentation style should get more exposure. One way to see the contest entries is <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/contest/worlds-best-presentation-contest-2009/entries?order=popularity">by votes</a>, so the ones with the most votes show on top. Dan&#8217;s presentation is currently #10, less than 200 votes behind the top spot. But you can only vote once per account. So if you see a presentation you like and give it your vote, it is gone forever.</p>
<p>Dan wrote <em><a href="http://www.thebackofthenapkin.com/">The Back of the Napkin</a></em> which is also the name of the blog he maintains. I enjoyed this book, and I think you should too.</p>
<p>The idea: all of the world&#8217;s problems can be solved by drawing. And even if you think you can&#8217;t draw, as most adults, it&#8217;s much simpler than it seems and it&#8217;s quite fun.</p>
<p>Problems can be reduced to 6 types of questions: who/what, how many, how, where, when and why. Each of these questions can be associated with a broad type of representation, for instance &#8220;where?&#8221; questions can be solved by a map where different elements are plotted. So that&#8217;s one way of categorizing visual representations.</p>
<p>The other axis that the author develops is what he calls SQUID. Depending on your audience, what you want to show may be:</p>
<ul>
<li> <strong>s</strong>imple or elaborate,</li>
<li><strong>q</strong>uality vs quantity,</li>
<li><strong>v</strong>ision vs execution,</li>
<li><strong>i</strong>ndividual vs comparison,</li>
<li>change (<strong>D</strong>elta) or as-is.</li>
</ul>
<p>The combination of the SQUID framework and the who, how many, how, where, when, and why questions lead you to one logical choice of representation, which will work make your audience go &#8220;a-ha&#8221; &#8211; guaranteed.</p>
<p>The logic holds, although I feel he tweaked his process for most if not all of the examples in the book. Anyway, this line of thought can easily be reproduced and can solve problems. Now the hand-drawn style is not necessary to this process, but is a nice touch. I&#8217;ve used it in presentations and it gets attention and sympathy. I was amazed to see how much easier and quicker it is to draw a visual that works by hand than with a user-friendly software. I&#8217;m enclined to think that the corporate world would be much more interesting (and fun) if there were more drawings and fewer word documents.</p>
<p>For those reasons, <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/danroam/healthcare-napkins-all">go vote for Dan Roam</a>.</p>
<h2>Update</h2>
<p><a href="http://www.slideshare.net/contest/worlds-best-presentation-contest-2009">Dan Roam won</a>! congratulations!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2009/09/02/slidesharenet-2009-contest-im-endorsing-dan-roam/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The state of presentations in 2008</title>
		<link>/2008/12/17/the-state-of-presentations-in-2008/</link>
		<comments>/2008/12/17/the-state-of-presentations-in-2008/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2008 12:41:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[presentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2008]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Al Gore]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[An Inconvenient Truth]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[criticism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[garr reynolds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guidelines]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[images]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nancy Duarte]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[powerpoint]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presentation zen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[slide:ology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[slideshare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[slideware]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Steve Jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tools]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[typography]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=112</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There have been many changes in how people understand presentations in 2008. How far have we gone? In 2008, 2 major books on the topic have been published. Presentation Zen, by Garr Reynolds, and slide:ology, by Nancy Duarte. People are accepting that a well-executed presentation can change the world. An Inconvenient Truth got nothing less <a class="read-more" href="/2008/12/17/the-state-of-presentations-in-2008/">&#8230;&#160;<span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There have been many changes in how people understand presentations in 2008. How far have we gone?</p>
<p>In 2008, 2<strong> major books on the topic have been published</strong>. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0321525655?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=jeromecukiern-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0321525655">Presentation Zen</a>, by Garr Reynolds, and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0596522347?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=jeromecukiern-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0596522347">slide:ology</a><img style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=jeromecukiern-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=0596522347" border="0" alt="" width="1" height="1" />, by Nancy Duarte.</p>
<p><strong>People are accepting that a well-executed presentation can change the world</strong>. <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B000ICL3KG?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=jeromecukiern-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=B000ICL3KG">An Inconvenient Truth</a><img style="border:none !important; margin:0px !important;" src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=jeromecukiern-20&amp;l=as2&amp;o=1&amp;a=B000ICL3KG" border="0" alt="" width="1" height="1" /> got nothing less than 2 academy awards and a nobel prize. And rumors about the health of master presenter Steve Jobs caused the stock markets to panic.</p>
<p>People are also finding that <strong>tools to create successful presentations are incredibly commonplace</strong>. From a technical standpoint, anyone with a computer could have created &#8220;<a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=U&amp;start=1&amp;q=http://www.youtube.com/watch%3Fv%3DpMcfrLYDm2U&amp;ei=ZexISZ_WN4zY0gXax5wP&amp;sig2=aVpciv4dx5iCWcZLlEr0ag&amp;usg=AFQjCNFCz0fx7wPiD-xtxo89i25mdVC78w">shift happens</a>&#8220;, which has been viewed by 5 to 10 million people.</p>
<p>As a result, <strong>blogs are now swarming with sensible presentation advice</strong>. A google query for &#8220;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_By_Powerpoint">death by powerpoint</a>&#8221; returns <a href="http://www.google.com/search?q=death+by+powerpoint">397000 hits</a> today. A year ago, searching for presentation tips yielded ideologic (as opposed to evidence-based) guidelines such as &#8220;no more than 7 bullets per slide&#8221; or &#8220;one slide per minute&#8221;. (you can still find those as well).</p>
<p>2008 was also the year where <strong>Slideshare took off</strong>. Not only did the viewership and amount of contents increase drastically, but the quality, relevancy and sophistication of the best presentations is now incredible. Empowered by inspring examples, clear guidelines and adequate tools, many are thriving to emulate great presenters.</p>
<p>So if I just end here, one could conclude that the world is definitely saved from ineffective presentations. The reality is slightly different.</p>
<p>This year, I have seen so far approximately 400 live presentations, and god knows how many online. Some were excellent, many were good, most were at least adequate. But a good proportion of them were still boring and I&#8217;d be lying if I claimed I could remember as much as 10% of them.</p>
<p>One explanation I came up with for that is that many presenters are still focusing on the final deliverable product rather than the fundamentals. These folks are very sensitive to advice like &#8220;mind your typography&#8221;, &#8220;illustrate your slides with large images&#8221;, or &#8220;forget bullets&#8221;. Now typography or images are important and can make a difference between a good and an excellent presentation. But it&#8217;s crucial to have a message to deliver and to focus on that message.</p>
<p>Bulleted texts are accused of cluttering the presentations. But if every little point or anecdote is illustrated with a vividly-colored image, then the images themselves become the clutter and clog everyone&#8217;s limited attention. You&#8217;d remember the images and cool effects but not the point. And a week later, you&#8217;ll have forgotten the images and the presentation altogether.</p>
<p>So my own piece of advice is that your big images won&#8217;t make your presentation. Your angle,  structure and consistency will. The best advice I got from Presentation Zen was to prepare a presentation away from a computer and only produce it once it&#8217;s final. It works. It really does.</p>
<p>Once this will be an accepted practice, seminars, classes and meetings will be much more exciting (let&#8217;s hope!).</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2008/12/17/the-state-of-presentations-in-2008/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Book review: Presentation Zen by Garr Reynolds</title>
		<link>/2008/11/26/book-review-presentation-zen-by-garr-reynolds/</link>
		<comments>/2008/11/26/book-review-presentation-zen-by-garr-reynolds/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2008 12:29:13 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[book review]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presentation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[advice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[book]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[garr]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[garr reynolds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guidelines]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[image]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[powerpoint]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[presentation zen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[slides]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[story]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[visual]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=15</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Presentation Zen, by Garr Reynolds, has been my favorite business book in 2008. Whatever your field, if you are a professional, chances are that you are going to make a presentation at least once a year. If you are looking for guidance, you could do worse than checking Garr&#8217;s website, aptly named presentation zen, or <a class="read-more" href="/2008/11/26/book-review-presentation-zen-by-garr-reynolds/">&#8230;&#160;<span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/0321525655?tag=jeromecukiern-20&amp;camp=14573&amp;creative=327641&amp;linkCode=as1&amp;creativeASIN=0321525655&amp;adid=1SMVEYMJTKAVERYAM6YM&amp;"><img class="alignleft" style="padding:10px;" title="Presentation Zen cover" src="http://sixminutes.dlugan.com/wp-content/uploads/2008/01/presentation-zen-book.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="245" /></a>Presentation Zen, by Garr Reynolds, has been my favorite business book in 2008.</p>
<p>Whatever your field, if you are a professional, chances are that you are going to make a presentation at least once a year. If you are looking for guidance, you could do worse than checking Garr&#8217;s website, aptly named <a href="http://www.presentationzen.com/">presentation zen</a>, or buying the book.</p>
<p>Garr&#8217;s book will not teach you everything you need to know about presentations, but is a great starting point.</p>
<p>If I were to summarize the book in one sentence, that would be:</p>
<p><strong>Focus on your delivering your message.</strong></p>
<p>Anything in your presentation that doesn&#8217;t help you deliver your key message must be removed. Conversely, there are ways to present your content that can enhance your message. Consider them.</p>
<p>I could sum up his practical advice in 3 points.</p>
<ul>
<li>start to think offline.</li>
<li>in your favorite presentation software, start from a blank slide.</li>
<li>use visuals. And give your visuals all the space they need.</li>
</ul>
<div>Let&#8217;s ellaborate a bit.</div>
<div><strong>Start to think offline</strong></div>
<div>The first thing most business professionals would do when asked to design a presentation would be to fire up Powerpoint and create slides. Then, they will edit slides. Insert slides&#8230; remove slides. Edit them some more. Tweak the design&#8230; Insert that extra idea. Ah, but the slide is no longer aligned. So we&#8217;re back to more editing and more tweaking. The end result is often busy, neither consistent nor convincing. Sounds familiar?</div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a title="27062008661 by Nevon, on Flickr" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/nevon/2621789613/"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3162/2621789613_8153c4b7c5.jpg" alt="27062008661" width="400" height="300" /></a></p>
<div>The solution to that problem is to start working on your presentation offline &#8211; determine the outline, how to structure your talk, what to say on each slide&#8230; A nice way to do this is with post-its.</div>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a title="Outlining my dConstruct talk by adactio, on Flickr" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/adactio/2735966814/"><img class="aligncenter" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3136/2735966814_cce38ccc94.jpg" alt="Outlining my dConstruct talk" width="375" height="500" /></a></p>
<div>Post-its are easy to group and reposition, and if text doesn&#8217;t fit on a post it, it&#8217;s probably too wordy to put on a slide, anyway.</div>
<div><strong>Start from a blank template</strong></div>
<div>Powerpoint and others have trained us to think in terms of bulleted lists. But what an awful way of presenting information! When you&#8217;re showing a bulleted list, you&#8217;re reading out loud your slide, to an audience who has alreay read it by the time you get to point 2. Garr, in this <a href="http://www.presentationzen.com/presentationzen/2006/01/contrasts_in_pr.html">star wars-themed slide show,</a> shows how bulleted lists are the &#8220;dark side of the force&#8221; type of presentations.</div>
<div><strong>Use visuals</strong></div>
<div><a href="http://presentationzen.blogs.com/presentationzen/2005/10/the_lessig_meth.html">Famous presenters</a> each have their signature style, and Garr&#8217;s is the use of full-bleed image with minimal legends (and Gill Sans, but what&#8217;s wrong with that? I love Gill Sans). Full-bleed means that instead of integrating a smaller image in a template, you make it occupy all the space in the slide.</div>
<div><iframe src="https://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/295996" width="425" height="356" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe><br/></div>
<div>I won&#8217;t claim this is the single best way of presenting information, and by the way, neither does he. But it is fool-proof and easy to emulate. Finding the right image, which has never been that easy, and using it appropriately, will always have great impact.</div>
<div></div>
<div>In the book, Garr covers much more ground. It&#8217;s not only interesting, but it&#8217;s a nice read, and laced with examples you can actually use. I was quite surprised to see him redo charts I had done! (although, for my defense, they were never intended to be shown as is in a powerpoint).</div>
<div>If you need to buy one book on presentations, buy this book. If you think you don&#8217;t need a book on presentation, buy this book as well.</div>
<div></div>
<div>PS. Since the book has been released, I can see lots of presentations, on <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/">slideshare</a> or elsewhere, that apply the visual style of Garr&#8217;s (nice, appropriately-chosen images, caption kept to an essential) but forget the other part of the story, which is the structure of the overall presentation. Both aspects are vital and complementary.</div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2008/11/26/book-review-presentation-zen-by-garr-reynolds/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
