<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>statistics &#8211; jeromecukier.net</title>
	<atom:link href="http://localhost/tag/statistics/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Just another WordPress site</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 05:36:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.6.10</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Using data visualization to disinform</title>
		<link>/2009/07/02/using-data-visualization-to-disinform/</link>
		<comments>/2009/07/02/using-data-visualization-to-disinform/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2009 10:10:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chart]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[deception]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[disinform]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[manipualtion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[misleading]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[statistics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[VAT]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=153</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Two weeks ago I have been at DD4D conference, conveniently located at my workplace. I will write some more on DD4D, meanwhile you can see this post on infosthetics by Petra and Marian. One of the things that struck me at DD4D was that several talks were about either data visualization for advocacy, or for <a class="read-more" href="/2009/07/02/using-data-visualization-to-disinform/">&#8230;&#160;<span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Two weeks ago I have been at <a href="http://DD4D.net/">DD4D</a> conference, conveniently located at my workplace. I will write some more on DD4D, meanwhile you can see this post on <a href="http://infosthetics.com/archives/2009/07/dd4d_conference_coverage_best-of.html">infosthetics </a>by <a href="http://pages.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/~pneumann/">Petra</a> and <a href="http://www.mariandoerk.de/">Marian</a>.  One of the things that struck me at DD4D was that several talks were about either data visualization for advocacy, or for education purposes. One speaker said that data visualization could be used to <strong>protect </strong>people <strong>against those who</strong> use numbers to <strong>mislead and disinform</strong>.  Yesterday, I saw this typical example of such a manipulation, reminding of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lies,_damned_lies,_and_statistics">the famous Disraeli quote</a>.<br />
<img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-154" title="disinform" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/07/disinform.png" alt="disinform" width="440" height="309" /></p>
<p>This is a poster for restaurants to display. Yesterday, VAT for restaurants in France was cut from 19.6% to 5.5%. This is the result over 10 years of lobbying. Initially, restaurants asked for a VAT drop and committed to cut their listed prices accordingly. That cut in price would have attracted more consumers, eventually generating more profit and possibly more tax money. That would have been a win-win-win situation for the restaurant industry, the consumer and the state.</p>
<p>But eventually, the changes that restaurants have agreed to their price structure are as follow. They would cut the listed price of up to 10 menu items by 11.8% to &#8220;reflect the tax drop&#8221;. In exchange, they are allowed to display this poster, on which the <strong>c</strong><strong>hart ominously promises a massive price drop</strong>.</p>
<p>In reality, 11.8% is not enough to offset the VAT drop.</p>
<p>That should have been approximately 13.4%  or 100*(1.196/1.055 &#8211; 1) . Fast-food chains only have to drop some of their prices by 5% to get the poster.</p>
<p>The poster claims: &#8220;a cut in VAT is a cut in prices!&#8221;. But what happens really? For most items, listed price (incl tax) is unchanged, which means their actual <strong>prices</strong> <strong>raise by 13.4%</strong>. And for the discounted items, the sales price excluding tax still raises by 1.4% (or 7.7% for fast-food chains).</p>
<p>Is this what was implied by the chart?</p>
<p>In the past two weeks, I have collected more examples of shameless lies backed by seemingly official numbers and charts, and will continue to collect them.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2009/07/02/using-data-visualization-to-disinform/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>New data services 1: Google&#8217;s public data</title>
		<link>/2009/06/05/new-data-services-1-googles-public-data/</link>
		<comments>/2009/06/05/new-data-services-1-googles-public-data/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2009 13:31:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jerome]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[data publishing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data visualization]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web sites]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[google]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[public data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[statistics]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=140</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Google&#8217;s public data has been launched somewhat unexpectedly at the end of April 2009. The principle is as follows. When someone enters a search query that could be interpreted as a time series, Google displays a line graph of this time series before other results. Click on it, and you can do some more things <a class="read-more" href="/2009/06/05/new-data-services-1-googles-public-data/">&#8230;&#160;<span class="meta-nav">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Google&#8217;s public data has been launched somewhat unexpectedly at the end of April 2009.</p>
<p>The principle is as follows. When someone enters a search query that could be interpreted as a time series, Google displays a line graph of this time series before other results. Click on it, and you can do some more things with the chart.</p>
<p><img class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-142" title="googlepublicdata1" src="http://www.jeromecukier.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/googlepublicdata1-300x210.png" alt="googlepublicdata1" width="450" height="315" /></p>
<p>The name public data can seem ambiguous.</p>
<p>Public, in one sense, refers to official, government-produced statistics. But, for content, public is also the opposite of copyrighted. And here, a little bit of digging reveals that it&#8217;s clearly the latter sense. If you want this service to point to your data, it must be copyright-free.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve seen Hans Rosling (of Gapminder fame, now Google&#8217;s data guru) deliver a few speeches to national statisticians to which he expressed all the difficulties he had to access their data, and battle with formatting or copyright issues. So I can understand where this is coming from. However. Imagine the outcry if google.com decided to stop indexing websites which were not in the public domain!</p>
<p>Remember my <strong>find </strong>&gt; <strong>access </strong>&gt; <strong>process </strong>&gt; <strong>present </strong>&gt; <strong>share</strong> <a href="http://www.jeromecukier.net/?p=124">diagram</a>?</p>
<p>I&#8217;d expect that google will solve the <strong>find</strong> problem. After all, they&#8217;re search people. But they don&#8217;t! You&#8217;d find a time series if you enter its exact name in google. There is no such thing (yet, as I imagine it would be easy to fix) as a list of their datasets.</p>
<p>They don&#8217;t tackle the <strong>access</strong> problem either. Once you see the visualizations, you&#8217;re not any step closer to actually getting the  data. You can see them, point by point, by mousing over the chart. I was also disappointed by the inaccuracy of the citation of their datasets. I&#8217;d have imagined that they&#8217;d provide a direct link to their sources, but they only state which agency produced the dataset. And finding a dataset from an agency is not a trivial matter.</p>
<p>They don&#8217;t deal with process, but who will hold that against them? Now what they offer is a very nice, very crisp representation of data (<strong>presenting data</strong>). I was impressed how legible the interface remained with many data series on the screen, while respecting Google&#8217;s look and feel and colour code.</p>
<p>Finally, it is also possible to <strong>share </strong>charts. Or rather, you can have a link to an image generated by google&#8217;s chart API, which is more than decent. A link to this static image, and a link to the chart on google&#8217;s public data service, and that&#8217;s all you should need (except, obviously, a link to the data proper!)</p>
<p>Another issue comes from the selection of the data sets proper.</p>
<p>One of the datasets is the unemployment rates, which are available monthly and by USA county. Now I can understand the rationale to match a google query of &#8220;unemployment rates&#8221; to that specific dataset. But there are really many unemployment rates, depending on what you divide by what. <span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: mceinline;">(are we counting unemployed people? unemployed jobseekers? which definition of unemployment are we using &#8211; ILO&#8217;s, or the BLS&#8217;s? and against what is the rate calculated &#8211; total population? population of working age? total labour force?) But how could that work if you expand the system to another country? To obtain the same level of granularity (to a very narrow geographic location, to a period of a month) would require some serious cooking of the data, so you can&#8217;t have granularity, comparability and accuracy. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: mceinline;">I don&#8217;t think the system is sustainable. I don&#8217;t like the idea that it gives the impression to people that economic statistics can be measured in real time at any level, just like web usage statistics for instance. They can&#8217;t be just observed, they&#8217;re calculated by people. </span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: mceinline;">Google public data is still in its infancy. To have a usable list of the datasets, for instance, would alleviate much of my negarive comments on the system. But for the time being, I&#8217;m not happy with the orientation they&#8217;ve chosen.</span></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2009/06/05/new-data-services-1-googles-public-data/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
